- Announcer:
The following program
is a PBS Wisconsin
original production.
[gentle, dramatic music]
- Reverend Greg Lewis:
We have to talk about
that elephant in the room.
- Reggie Jackson:
Racism has been a part
of Wisconsin history
since the beginning as a state.
- Alex Lindenmeyer:
Gosh, as white folks,
we have so much to learn.
[somber music]
- Dr. Christy Clark-Pujara:
History can help us understand
why we are where we are.
[gentle music]
- Announcer: Funding for
Wisconsin in Black & White
is provided by
Ira and Ineva Reilly Baldwin
Wisconsin Idea Endowment,
DeAtley Family Foundation,
Joe and Mary Ellyn
Sensenbrenner,
Lau and Bea Christensen,
The Evjue Foundation,
the charitable arm
of The Capital Times,
Madison College,
National Guardian
Life Insurance Company,
UnityPoint Health -
Meriter,
donors to
the Focus Fund for Journalism,
and Friends
of PBS Wisconsin.
- Hello, I'm PBS Wisconsin
special projects journalist
Murv Seymour.
In a series of special reports,
we take an in-depth look
at systemic racism
here in Wisconsin.
Its history across the state
is painfully complex
and opens lots
of old and new wounds.
In this first episode of
Wisconsin in Black & White,
we take a look at history
and the criminal justice system.
- Professor Ion Meyn: There are
more Black Americans in prison
than white Americans right now.
That is, and should be,
completely shocking.
It is apartheid.
- Noble Wray: It takes a society
to look at this
in a different way.
- Secretary Kevin Carr:
That's a statistic
that I don't think any of us
should be proud of.
- Justice Jill Karofsky:
Oh, my God,
this is such a big problem.
- Murv: We ask the question,
"How did we get here?"
[door clatters]
[twinkling music]
[typewriter clicking]
- Jackson: Systemic racism means
that within that society,
you have factors
about people's lives
that you can predict
the outcomes of their lives
on the day that they're born,
based on the racial groups
that they belong to.
- Murv: Reggie Jackson
educates people about diversity.
- Racism has been a part
of Wisconsin history
since it began as a state.
I often times joke with people
that I call Wisconsin
"Wississippi"
because we generally think
of racism in the South.
- Dr. Christy Clark-Pujara:
Lincoln opposed
slavery's expansion,
not its existence.
- Seymour: Dr. Christy
Clark-Pujara is an author,
and she teaches
African American history
at the University
of Wisconsin- Madison.
- Systemic racism, much of it,
is an extension of the creation
of race-based slavery.
And race-based slavery
was created through law,
and that was done
in the colonial period.
- Jesus give you
some tough love.
Racism is huge
here in Wisconsin,
and it's worse
than it's ever been.
Milwaukee is kind of special.
This is the Selma of the North.
When I go to other places,
people don't even know
that Milwaukee
have Black folks living here.
Say, "There's Black folks
in Milwaukee?"
Yeah!
And they've been oppressed
like crazy. [laughs]
- Not surprisingly, the highest
demographic representation
of African Americans...
- Murv: University of Wisconsin
law professor
Ion Meyn teaches
race and the law,
civil rights,
and wrongful convictions.
- White society
is addicted to racism.
- Seymour: He has a lot to say
about the racial climate
in Wisconsin.
- I don't know
what makes Milwaukee
the most segregated city
in the United States.
It is.
And I don't know what makes
the practices in Milwaukee
generate an overrepresentation
of Black people in prison
so that it's the highest
in the nation.
If you're a Black person,
Black resident in Wisconsin,
you have a 12 times
higher chance
of being incarcerated
than a white Wisconsinite.
- Seymour: History tells us
the over-policing of Blacks
in Wisconsin
and across the country
dates back
to the end of slavery.
- When the 13th Amendment
to the Constitution
was ratified
in December of 1865,
most people never read
what it says.
- It abolishes slavery,
and then there's a semi-colon,
"Except for punishment
for those who have been
found guilty of a felony."
- It creates the ability
for you to be back in slavery
in a different form.
Something like loitering,
which had never been illegal
before, becomes illegal.
- Whistling in public.
Like, I mean,
like that level of nonsense.
Walking along a railroad track,
not being able to produce
employment papers on demand.
You steal a pig,
you go to prison for life.
- Instead of sending you
to prison,
someone who owns a plantation
or a mine
or some business
who wants some free labor,
they'll be able to come in
and grab you
and put you into that system
so that you're
not gonna go to prison.
Now you're gonna go back
and work for free.
- Society says, "Oh, my gosh,
Black people have a propensity
to commit crimes,"
versus what was going on,
which was they were
arresting Black people
for committing no crime, and
then sending them to slavery.
- Seymour: The small town
of Appleton
was once the center of one
of the most racist tactics used
across the country to keep
Blacks out of white communities.
- Meyn: Appleton doesn't really
have any Black people,
and if you asked people
in Appleton,
it's just because Black people
didn't wanna move there.
Black people lived in Appleton
before the 1880s,
and they attempted to join
a growing community
during the '40s and '50s,
but it was a sundown town
through 1970
and enforced by the police.
- Seymour: Sundown towns
were places
that didn't allow Blacks
and other people of color
after dark.
- Jackson: They were
all over Wisconsin.
- Seymour: Nearly 250 in all,
according to a database
created by Washington, D.C.
sociologist James Loewen.
- Dr. Christy Clark-Pujara:
So, Black people
can be there as workers,
they can come to fish
during the day,
but you'd better
be out by night.
- Jackson: Some places
had a horn that would ring
in the evening when it was time
for Black people to get out.
Some places literally had signs
on the side of the roadway
that said, you know,
"After the sun sets,
Black people,
you're not welcome here."
- Seymour: About that time,
the prison population
in Wisconsin
and everywhere else
begins to explode.
[dramatic trumpet music]
- Reporter: Six days of rioting
in a Negro section
of Los Angeles left...
- Meyn: After the Watts riot,
white people blamed Black people
for the problem.
The response was a call
for federal funding
to provide a more
robust policing of these areas.
We started to see
this war on crime.
- Sec. Kevin Carr:
I'm aware that the current
criminal justice system
has a disproportionately large
number of persons of color
involved in it.
It makes me somewhat
sensitive to,
hopefully, being able
to address the needs
of that population in a way
that is fair to everyone.
- Seymour: Former Madison
police chief Noble Wray
sits on the governor's
pardon board.
- The politics back then
was tough on crime,
tough on drugs, say no to drugs.
It was, you know,
a zero-tolerance approach.
- You're not going to hire
all of these police officers
for them to sit around
and do nothing.
- Meyn: It was
billions of dollars.
- Officer 1:
Open the ####ing door,
or I'm gonna break
the ####ing window.
- Officer 2:
Open the door, man.
- Meyn: It was changing the face
of corrections and policing.
- Officer 1: So if
you cooperate...
- All of that money focused
on those communities of color.
- You end up with
a disproportionate population
that are under
the criminal justice system.
- If you live in the quote,
unquote hood and poor areas,
you are policed in a way
that people in affluent areas
are not, right?
And so you are just more likely
to find yourself
in front of a judge.
- White individuals,
their cases get dismissed
at a rate 50% higher
than the Black individuals.
There's a higher rate
of sentencing Black individuals
for the same crime,
at every part of the system.
By the way,
there's a higher rate
of Black individuals
for the same thing
being sent to a higher level
of security prison.
And then there's a higher rate
of white people in prison
getting good time credits
than Black people.
If you look at every part
of the system,
it doesn't matter
where you look.
You're going to find
these drivers of disparity.
- Seymour: Today,
former governor Tommy Thompson
and others admit
building more prisons
was the wrong approach.
Now retired, Thompson
is a passionate advocate
for more educational
opportunities
for those incarcerated.
- The increased crime indicated
that we needed more prisons
at the time,
and which I accommodated.
But every time I did this,
I always tried to balance
on the other side.
I was big on welfare reform.
I was big
on workforce development.
on expanding education.
- Domineé Meek:
In February of 1992,
I had been expelled...
- Seymour: At age 15,
Domineé Meek received
a life sentence
for taking the life
of Warren Smith, Junior,
an innocent bystander.
Domineé believes he and other
Black and brown teens
receive harsher sentences
compared with whites
the same age,
convicted of the same crime.
- Domineé Meek:
When I was incarcerated,
I only met one person
that was white
that was sentenced as a juvenile
to life in prison.
They took Black boys
and said that
"Y'all are Black men."
And they punished us like men.
They don't do that
to white boys.
Not in the numbers.
They gave them help.
- In Wisconsin,
the number of, kind of,
criminal referrals
is three times higher
for Black kids than white kids.
- You got two or three
generations of Black parents
who have been incarcerated.
The majority of the people
locked up are Black and brown.
So when you got
the majority of us locked up,
you can't be a parent
from prison.
So when that child
looks for that,
only place he goes to get it
is in the streets.
So we need father figures
to step up,
somebody to be,
that I can call
at 2 o'clock in the morning
and say,
"Murv, I'm locked up,
can you come get me?"
Or "Murv, I'm scared,
Or "Murv,"
and when I disappoint Murv,
that still
is gonna love me
like Murv would love
his own children.
- Seymour: In 2020,
Domineé walked out
of Oakhill Correctional
Institution after 28 years.
He says he doesn't feel free.
- When I left prison
in September,
one hole was filled,
but one wasn't.
Warren can never come back
and hug his mama,
hug his baby girl.
I live my happiness,
and I live this life,
but I never forget about Warren.
The goal is to prevent
another Domineé
from killing another Warren.
- Seymour: Domineé
is a former student
of Odyssey Beyond Bars,
a college jumpstart program
at Oakhill.
Peter Moreno runs it
on behalf of the
University of Wisconsin,
out of four institutions
in the state.
- We've learned
through experience
that long prison sentences,
while they may be appropriate
for certain crimes,
are not appropriate
for a lot of crimes.
And long prison sentences,
combined with a lack
of programming in the prisons,
can be especially harmful
because we're keeping people
in an environment
where they're unable to learn,
unable to grow,
unable to socialize,
and then we're letting them
go back to their communities,
expecting them to do well.
- Seymour: Moreno encourages
a closer look
at the conditions
of neighborhoods
and fixing problems
leading to people
entering the criminal justice
system.
- We know how to deal
with many of these issues.
- Seymour: With the recidivism
rate of just over 31%,
Wray says there are
four support systems
proven to help close
the sometimes-revolving door
back to prison.
- Do you have a place to live
when you get out,
and is that place solid,
does it reinforce,
does it support you?
Two, do you have employment,
which is big.
Three, do you have the people
around you that support you
and that will help you in terms
of doing the right things,
making the right decisions?
And the fourth one is treatment.
- Wisconsin should be
less worried about
getting a bad rap
and more worried
about improving the lives
of the people in this state
who live
in our communities of color.
- Seymour: In 2016, Supreme
Court Justice Jill Karofsky
took part in a course called
"Justified Anger: Black History
for a New Day."
The program was run by the
Madison organization Nehemiah,
which focuses on strengthening
the African American community
in Wisconsin.
Justice Karofsky says
the course
on racial disparities
in the criminal justice system
gave her a new understanding
of how, at times,
the criminal justice system
unfairly impacts
people of color.
- This country was founded
by white men
who were well-intentioned
and who created a system of laws
and the Constitution
that was built
on the idea of freedom.
But back in the late 1700s,
we know that they didn't mean
freedom for all people.
Because of that,
it has been the white majority
who has been in control
of so much of this country.
Business, of government,
of the financial world.
It is gonna need to be
leaders in those areas
that are going to have to help
make the change
that so many of us
wanna see.
- Seymour: Justice Karofsky says
inspiration from attending
"Justified Anger"
led her to bring the Nehemiah
anti-racism trainings
to other judges across the state
in the form of intense,
one-day sessions.
- Do you think that we have
too much emphasis
on race these days?
- No.
Most Supreme Court justices
don't do interviews like this.
The reason I am doing this
interview and I agreed to do it
is because I think, and I
believe, and I know, and I see
that it is a problem
in our state,
and maybe if I stand up
and sit here,
as uncomfortable
as it may be for me,
that that may help
be part of the change.
One of the ways we can do that
is to try to reach out
to our colleagues of color,
to mentor them,
to learn from them
because their experience
is very, very rich
and could be different
than ours.
And then, to help them succeed,
should they wanna run for judge,
or should they wanna ask
for an appointment.
- Seymour: Secretary Carr says
he sees a shift
from simply locking people up
for public safety
to providing more treatment,
more education,
more trauma-based care.
- We have started
to rely more on alternatives
to revocations,
such as short-term sanctions
and community-based programming,
and for instance,
like drug treatment referral
for minor possession cases
as opposed to sending
that person back to prison.
- Each of us needs to figure out
what is it that we can do.
If it's only one thing,
then it's only one thing.
- Alex: We really wanted to have
a brick-and-mortar space,
like, in the heart of the city
where people could
come together.
- Seymour: Short Stack Eatery
in Madison
serves up
a lot more than food.
- Alex: Gosh, as white folks,
we have so much to learn.
[bell dings]
- Seymour: Its owner says
their spot serves as an example
of how to help equalize
what they consider
the uneven intersections
of race and inequality.
- Alex Lindenmeyer: We're
definitely unapologetically
trying to become less and less
racist every day. [laughs]
That's our goal.
We figure if we can unravel
some of our racist tendencies
and indoctrinations,
everybody can.
- Seymour: At her restaurant,
Lindenmeyer's job applications
look different.
There is no box to check
if you have a felony conviction.
- The fact that we don't have
a box on our application,
and we don't do
background checks,
and we don't do drug testing,
and all those things.
- Seymour: For years, they have
also routinely sent its managers
to the Nehemiah's nine-week
"Justified Anger" course.
- We have huge, huge systems
to figure out
how to disassemble
and reassemble,
and so it's gonna be
lifelong work.
- They said 92%
of our community
didn't even know that
there was a mayoral election.
- Alex: Black folks
can't do it alone.
They can't do it without us.
We're the one
causing the violence.
- Stop running people over here
out in these streets.
Stop shooting folks, man.
Yeah, they need to fix it.
We ain't gonna fix that, man.
We're the hated ones.
[gentle music]
- We continue
our reporting on race
and the criminal justice
system in Wisconsin.
We are here at Short Stack
Eatery in Madison,
and we are joined by the owner
of Short Stack Eatery,
Alex Lindenmeyer,
and we've also got Dr. Alex Gee
of Nehemiah's
"Justified Anger" project,
and Carl Fields,
who is with EXPO,
which stands for EX-
incarcerated People Organizing,
and he's also representing
Wisdom, a faith-based group
that operates out of the state
of Wisconsin.
Alex, I wanna start with you.
You mentioned,
during our pre-interview,
that you felt like
Wisconsin business owners
could do more to help
impact the disparity
that we see in the
criminal justice system.
What do you think
they can learn
from some of the things
that you're doing here?
And I'd love to hear what you
guys have to say about it, too.
- People that are
justice-involved
have so many things
that they're dealing with.
So employers need to internally
start having
the conversation about
what the criminal justice system
even looks like now.
If you're not justice-involved,
or you don't have
a family member,
or you don't have an employee
that's justice-involved,
it's designed on purpose
for you to not care,
for you to not know.
And so employers really need
to get educated internally
about what's going on
and what these barriers are
that people are up against,
and then figure out how
they can set up support systems
within their culture
and within their organization
to make sure people
get what they need.
- Yeah, we know that
you purposefully hire folks
that do have barriers.
Carl, how does that help folks
that are transitioning?
- To know that
there are companies
that are sticking
to what society intended
for criminal justice
to be is huge,
and that is tangible
to say, "Yeah,
"oh, you paid your dues,
come on.
"We, not only will we like
to work with you,
"but we'd be honored to
"because you got something
you wanna show,
you got something
you wanna prove."
And we're also
creating opportunities
that that's a real job,
you know, opportunity
to give to somebody who is
really in need of that.
- And Doctor, your organization
runs a re-entry program?
- Dr. Alex Gee:
It does; it does.
- And how do you see businesses
being able to impact things?
- If we want to attract large
businesses to this community,
where again,
there's low unemployment,
we have to help people
who are in this community,
wanting to work, willing
to work, to become employed.
So one of the things that we do
through our re-entry program
is we help to find jobs
for men and women,
particularly men,
with our programming,
to find jobs, you know.
My vice president for re-entry,
a gentleman named
Anthony Cooper,
has placed over 1,000 men over
the past eight or nine years.
That's significant because
when you come out of prison,
and you have stable employment,
you can have stable housing,
which means you can live
a stable life in the community,
and it drastically reduces
the temptation to recidivize.
So we have a responsibility
to our own state's economy
and to the well-being
of good people.
We need them in order
for our economy to be stronger
in this community.
- I would love to hear
what you folks think
are some of the
biggest challenges
facing our criminal justice
system.
- You know, when we talk about,
you know,
alternatives to whether it be
a deferment program
through the court on pretrial,
or during incarceration,
or post-incarceration,
those programs,
those options that come up
are always met
with a zero margin of error.
And that is so problematic to me
because the current system
and what it produces
is not held to any sort
of standard on that level,
but in fact, does have
a low effectiveness rate.
But we can't seem to take some
chances to try something else
because it's not politically
advantageous always.
It's not classy; it's not sexy.
- What role do you think
our federal government
and our state government,
what role do you think they play
in affecting the
criminal justice system
here in the state?
- I think that these
governmental agencies
need to really own up
to the fact that
this criminal system
is really producing what
it was designed to produce,
this ugly, ugly cycle.
It needs to be called out
and dismantled
so we can build something
that's equitable
and that really
does rehabilitate.
- The history
of how systems were built
and what they were built for,
that plays out, continues
to play out even to this day,
a hundred-plus years later,
and that is a weight on any
person who enters the system.
As an ex-knucklehead myself,
turned professional,
I messed up in life,
I made some poor choices,
but no one anywhere
in the criminal justice system
told me that felonies
were gonna be forever.
I've seen that the barriers
just continue,
seen that no matter what I do
or how much of a great effort
I put forward,
society's still allowed to
socially acceptably mistreat me.
- You could buy someone a house
and send them to college
for what it costs, you know,
at least put a down payment
on a house,
for what it costs
to incarcerate.
So what are we
really trying to do?
We have the money;
why are we locking people up
when we could use resources
or redirect them
to really help people
out of a hole?
- I learned in my reporting the
term 'crimeless revocations.'
I'd love to get you to,
you know,
let our viewers know
what it exactly means
and how it leads and feeds
the pipeline to prison.
- The working definition
of a crimeless revocation
is placing a person into prison
or placing a person
back into incarceration
for not having
committed a new crime,
but for a technical violation
or rules violation of some kind.
- The way that plays out
specifically is perhaps
you bought a car and didn't
get it cleared with your agent.
- Alex: Yeah,
you used a computer.
- You used a computer.
You got married
and didn't ask for permission.
I know that
those are some extreme things,
but I know folks who have
feared for their lives
or their freedom for doing
things just like that.
But just think about this,
the crazy numbers,
to Alex's point,
of people in prison
are folks who have returned
on technicalities.
- We look at states like Oregon,
we look at states
like Washington,
that are putting huge dollars
into programs
of figuring out how to get
parents things they need
while they're locked up,
figuring out how
to get families reunited
while folks are locked up,
figuring how to get families
that have somebody locked up
the resources they need.
And our state has a lot
of catching up to do, for sure.
- Minnesota has a comparable
demographic to Wisconsin,
but they don't incarcerate
nearly as much as we do.
It really is big business.
That's not just cliché;
it's really big business.
- Another learning process
I went through in this reporting
is I learned about language,
and I learned that
I'm guilty of saying some things
that, you know,
aren't humanizing people.
How important is
the language of incarceration?
- When we're talking about
felons or convicts or inmates,
you know, last I checked,
I was a person,
and I continue to be that.
And so person-first language
is something
that we've been driving on
in this work that we do
for quite some time.
- It's the language that
helps us to reinforce barriers.
"This person can't be trusted,
"I don't want you
around my family,
you can't come to my church,
you can't work at my job,"
so it begins
with even the language.
And again, what it conjures
in our minds
about what this person
is capable of,
but when you use
those terminologies,
you don't really think that
they're really ex or former.
It's just you did some time,
but you're still
in that same place,
and that's why
we keep that same title.
We just put ex in front of it.
- I have employees that go
to UW who are 19 and white,
and I have employees
who are 45 on paper,
and we have some disparities,
some differences,
and if we actually
wanna figure out
how to make this a safe place
for everybody to work,
it's a lot of internal
conversation about things like,
"Hey, you can't say convict,
you can't say felon,
here's why."
We gotta figure out
how we got here.
I can preach at you
all this stuff
about the lingo
and the language,
and why it's ineffective
or what have you,
but until people
have a basis
or an understanding
of how we ended up here,
it's a moot point.
- And Dr. Gee,
how do we get all Wisconsinites
to get vested on this?
- I don't even know
if that's my expectation,
but if I can have an impact
on employers
and their new employees,
or individuals who want
to make a difference.
When you invest in people
who wanna make a difference,
you trust
in a ripple effect.
But I've learned
that if I want
to live a healthier
and longer life,
I can't keep beating my head
against the wall
for people who wanna
argue these points.
I need to take the time
to invest in people
who wanna be allies,
who wanna speak out,
and who want to make sure
that everyone
has judicial justice
in their lives.
And so I try to invest
in the people
who want to be
a part of the change
and hope that,
at some point,
we will have an impact
on Wisconsin,
but I don't go after
the whole state.
I just try to really
work with the people
who want to get it.
- We're gonna have
to leave it there.
Thank you all for being here;
Dr. Gee.
- My pleasure.
- Mr. Fields.
- Sir.
- Alex Lindenmeyer,
on behalf of PBS Wisconsin
and our crew,
we appreciate you
for providing a space for us
to have this
important conversation.
- My pleasure.
- And we thank you folks
for joining us, too.
[somber music]
In this episode
of Wisconsin in Black & White,
we took a look
at the history
of race and education
in this state.
Educators and students weigh in
on longtime challenges
Black and brown students face
in the classrooms
throughout Wisconsin,
and we hear about
the work being done
to increase opportunity
and put all students
on equal footing.
[children laughing]
[teacher sounds out letter 'D']
- Children: Oh.
- Look at how Black students are
doing.
It is... terrible.
[gentle, somber music]
- Whatever efforts there have
been by the federal government
to create integrated schools
have not worked.
- Education is the conduit
to freedom.
- We have a lot more work
to do.
- Murv Seymour: Wisconsin.
- We're a microcosm
of the nation.
- We want to create change.
- Seymour: A conversation
about race and education
in this state.
- It is a complex one.
We've never given full
education access to everyone.
- Seymour:
Author and retired University of
Wisconsin Education Professor,
Dr. Gloria Ladson-Billings,
travels the world
learning, teaching, and
training people about education.
- It's Thomas Jefferson
who says,
"Listen, we are not gonna be
able to maintain a democracy
unless the common folks
are educated."
- It goes all the way
to the Wisconsin Supreme Court.
- Seymour:
Dr. Christy Clark-Pujara
is a UW-Madison
history professor,
and also works with the
Madison Organization, Nehemiah.
She's an instructor
in its Justified Anger
"Black History
for a New Day" course.
Nehemiah focuses
on strengthening
the African American community
in Wisconsin.
The nine-week course
teaches people
about race, history,
and justice.
She and Ladson-Billings help
explain why the playing field
of education began to take shape
out of balance
across the country,
including here in Wisconsin.
- Dr. Christy Clark-Pujara:
The laws against
teaching enslaved people to read
actually come into play
after the founding
of the nation,
in response to
enslaved people
doing things
like forging fake passes.
- Seymour: Written by
their owners,
passes were required for
slaves to leave the plantation
for extra work or errands.
- When we're talking
about access to education,
post-slavery, you just have
cities, states,
and counties
not investing
in the education
of Black people,
who are taxpayers.
They would have
inferior school buildings,
inferior materials, inferior
books, or notebooks, right?
The teachers
were paid less.
And so, it was
an active disinvestment.
My father was
functionally illiterate.
His family was poor,
and he was sharecropping cotton
most of his life,
and his labor was essential
to his family's survival,
and the school that
he could attend was underfunded.
- Seymour: During the
civil rights era,
Milwaukee was
the epicenter of protests,
demanding compliance
to end continued segregation
in schools.
- We tend to think about
the Civil Rights Movement,
like the institution of slavery,
as something that is uniquely
Southern, and it was not.
- Seymour:
While the US Supreme Court's
Brown versus
the Board of Education ruling
in the late 1950s
ordered all US schools
to desegregate,
Milwaukee and other parts
of the state,
like much of the nation,
didn't do so for decades.
- The schools in Milwaukee
are not in line
with Brown versus the Board
of Education until 1979.
- Reggie Jackson:
The city of Milwaukee's
public school system decided,
"Well, we're gonna
build new schools,
but we're gonna build them
on the south side,
which is primarily
the white part of town, right?"
- The schools that Black people
have access to
were severely underfunded.
- Ion Meyn: What you saw
in Black communities
was a continual kind of
decline in the tax base,
and the ability to
support public education
in those communities.
- Seymour: A declining
tax base
due to declining property
values in housing like this
in Milwaukee.
- Housing policy
is education policy.
You go to the schools
in your neighborhood,
and we tend to fund schools
through property taxes.
Better than 60%
of Black and brown kids
still go
to segregated schools.
- Seymour: Schools in
the Milwaukee metro area
are more segregated
for Black and white students
than any other metro area
of the country.
That's comparing
Milwaukee schools
to those
in the surrounding counties
of Ozaukee, Washington,
and Waukesha.
- Whatever efforts there have
been by the federal government
to create integrated
schools have not worked.
- There are many white children
who go to all-white districts,
and nobody says, "Oh, this is
a segregated district."
They say, "This is
a good district."
If you look at performance,
Black and brown kids
continue to lag.
- Seymour: Those students test
below white students in math,
in the early grades,
and it's not just math.
- It speeds
over a hundred miles an hour.
- Seymour: If there's
one indicator
of how students will perform...
- Woman: Reading proficiency
is important
across the races.
- Seymour: ...It's their ability
to read by 3rd grade,
and state assessments show
that just one year later
in the 4th grade,
reading scores for Black and
Hispanic students also lag.
- The most revolutionary
thing we could do
is teach these kids
how to read.
Whoa!
[leaf blower humming]
- Seymour: But educators
across Wisconsin are working
to reverse these trends.
At One City grade
school in Madison,
the focus on reading is key.
- Yeah! It kind
of continues on.
- Seymour: 3rd grade teacher,
Kirsty Blattner
teaches reading skills
at this public charter
where more than
80% of the students
are Black, Hispanic,
or multiracial.
Blattner is passionate
about making sure
her students embrace reading.
- Kirsty Blattner: I have a deep
passion for helping scholars
that are struggling
academically.
If you have a scholar
that doesn't feel confident
and comfortable with reading,
then they'll find other ways
to sort of mask that.
Because no one wants to be seen
as not knowing.
Instead of, "I can't do this,
I can't do this yet."
Instead of,
"I'm not good at this."
"What are you good at?
Would you like
to be good at this?"
- Sara Shaw: America has trouble
talking about race, period.
- Seymour: Sara Shaw
researches education
for a nonprofit think
tank out of Milwaukee,
called the Wisconsin
Policy Forum.
- There's a trope
in literacy circles that
before 3rd grade, students are
learning how to read.
And after 3rd grade,
students are
reading to be able to learn.
Think of how many
of your daily activities
become more difficult.
Everything from reading
street signs, to menus,
to engaging in the legal system,
or going to the doctor's office.
- Education is the
conduit to freedom.
- Seymour: From grade school
achievement to high school
where one superintendent
can boast the benefits
of a diverse student body.
- Tremayne Clardy:
We're approximately
35% students of color here
in the Verona Area
School District.
We celebrate diversity here
in the Verona Area
School District,
and we understand
that a diverse clientele
in the students
that we serve
allows us to be
a better district.
- Seymour: Inside
the district's signature
$150 million high school,
Verona Area
school superintendent
Dr. Tremayne Clardy
is straightforward
about his commitment
and obligation
to create equity for
all students in his district,
especially those
that are Black and brown.
- It is our responsibility
to move barriers
but never, never
lowering expectations.
- Seymour: While recent
statewide data
shows a gap
in the graduation rates
of Black and brown students
compared to white students,
Dr. Clardy and other educators
believe the difference in
achievement
has less to do with performance,
and more to do
with something else.
- It's opportunity.
It's definitely not skill.
It's not intellect.
There's not any other
internal barrier
on behalf of
our Black and brown students.
It is purely about access.
- Seymour: Opportunity and
access are why this school
has windows in place of walls,
and wide-open common spaces.
- We are modeling, you know,
other students seeing
that collaborative process.
We set up our
furniture that way.
We set up the classroom
structure that day,
because you know the power
of peer-to-peer interaction,
and what that means
to strengthening education.
- Carri: What is that thing
that's in you?
- Seymour: Meet guidance
counselor Carri Hale.
- There's no typical day
in the world
of a high school counselor.
- Seymour: In the spirit
of strengthening education,
in 2018, the district sent her,
and every other teacher
to the Nehemiah Justified Anger
"Black History
for a New Day" course.
- We really had to get
to the root and heart
of the history of the systems
that have caused
barriers that
we're trying to dismantle.
- Seymour: For Carri Hale...
- It just fed me.
- Seymour: ...the course
has been life changing.
- It's just grown in me
over the years,
and I realized at that time,
there was so much I didn't know.
It benefits me as an educator
so that when I'm working
with a student
who doesn't look like me
or their family
speaks another language,
whatever it might be,
that I can
respect them and value them,
and see them, and honor them
for who they are
in this space we're in.
- Gerald Montgomery:
Well, I definitely struggled
trying to figure out who I was,
just like everybody else.
- Seymour: Senior Gerald
Montgomery says attending
this diverse high school
has made him more
culturally aware than ever.
- When I came here, it was
kind of like a cultural shock,
seeing not too many faces
looking like me.
- Seymour: It's one of
the reasons Gerald got involved
with the school's Black
student union group...
- It's just more of, like,
celebrating Black culture.
- Seymour: ...which anyone
can join.
- The first BSU year, it was,
like, small, like, 10 people,
when I was a freshman,
and now it's like 80.
And just seeing like that
group of Black folks around me,
I feel like that really helps
keeping, like, that balance
of me going through school
and everyday life.
- Seymour: Gerald says
he plans to go to college.
If he goes to a University
of Wisconsin school,
he'll be one of
a few Black students doing so.
Enrollment numbers
show that in 1975,
just 2.5% of students
were Black.
Nearly 50 years later,
their numbers in 2022
still make up just
2.9% of enrollment law.
While Professor Ion Meyn
believes the numbers
should mirror the demographics
of the nation's Black population
of about 14%.
- If that gets to 3%,
is that progress?
No.
We're not close to progress.
We're not close to even
reckoning with our problem.
- Seymour: The UW System lists
diversity as a core value,
and its five-year plan calls
for boosting African American
enrollment to 15% by 2028.
- Dr. Equan Burrows:
College is a aspiration
that is not afforded to all.
It's our honor to serve
and be one of the only
majority-minority institutions
in the state of Wisconsin.
- Seymour: Dr. Equan Burrows
is the dean of students
at Milwaukee Area
Technical College,
where more than half
the full-time student population
are minorities.
- It's important that we
level that playing field.
Look forward to
being the mentors.
- Seymour: Dr. Burrows
runs a mentoring program
with about
a hundred Black male students
called
the Men of Color Initiative.
- The goals are
to educate and empower students.
- Seymour: The program
hopes to give students
like Jeremiah Crawford a
better chance to finish college
and keep pace
with other students
who eventually
gain their bachelor's degree.
- Just kind of depends on...
- Jeremiah: I've always wanted
to go to college.
My home life was a shambles.
It was rough
having a father on drugs.
- Seymour: If that
wasn't enough.
- Jeremiah Crawford: High school
was a point where I started
to retreat into myself.
- Seymour: Jeremiah
has something else
that makes learning and life
more difficult.
- Jeremiah: My sickle cell
stood in the way.
- Seymour: He copes
with the blood disorder
sickle cell anemia.
- The last thing that you
wanna do is pick up a book,
and my illness
would just take over.
The Men of Color give us
an opportunity to meet,
and share our emotions
and our feelings,
and struggles we're having.
- Seymour: When it comes to
reading...
- It's a skill that
a lot of people are missing
in this day and age.
- Seymour: Jeremiah
knows its importance.
Every day he says he does...
- About an hour to two hours
of reading.
I would set an alarm
for 15 minutes.
Read, stop reading,
take a break.
- Seymour:
He agrees with experts
like Dr. Ladson-Billings
who say, reading about
things you like
organically leads
to more reading.
- If you like self-help books,
you should look for that.
If you want to learn
how to work on a car,
you should read
those type of books.
- I think that's really good;
I liked it.
- Seymour: Hitting the books
is often new
for a population
that schools can leave behind.
People whose incarceration
cut learning short.
An innovative program
hopes to change that.
- There are many,
many justifications
for higher education in prison.
- You opened up a really
important conversation.
- Seymour: This college
classroom is inside a prison.
Odyssey Beyond Bars
conducts this college-level
English composition course
at Racine Correctional
and three other prisons
across the state,
on behalf
of the University of Wisconsin.
- Peter: It transforms
how they look at their lives.
Virtually all of our students
have reported to us
at the end of the class
that the
experience in Odyssey
has made them want to
take more college classes.
There are people in prison
who look around and think,
"I don't ever want
to be back here again,
"and I want to do something
about my life
that ensures that I don't."
- I gave the, quote
commencement speech
at Oakwood Correctional Center.
- Seymour: Each time,
Dr. Ladson-Billing says,
she'd ask one question.
- "Raise your hand
if you were ever suspended?"
I've never had less than
100% of the hands go up.
[gentle poignant music]
- Seymour: Suspensions
and expulsions from high school
can lead to what
has been called,
"the school-to-prison pipeline,"
and at the very least,
disrupt graduation,
and college attainment.
- Now the prisons
are having to go back and say,
"Listen, let's make sure
you get the education
you should have gotten."
- Seymour: If fixing
the opportunity gap
for Black and brown students
is a puzzle,
another important piece of it
is the shortage
of minority teachers.
- They talked about
how my dad would move out,
and how me and my sister...
- Our students want and deserve
to see someone
that looks like them.
- Seymour: For his part,
Superintendent Clardy is proud
of his efforts in his district
to diversify its staff
with people like Kabby Hong,
Teacher of the Year.
- And then, if you look
at this paragraph.
For so many kids of color,
they've never had
a teacher of color.
A lot of the university programs
are not diverse.
So if your feeder pool
of teacher applicants
is not diverse,
then, of course,
you're not gonna have
a diverse
teaching workforce.
- Seymour: In 2020, researchers
at the Wisconsin Policy Forum
took an extensive look
into the racial diversity
of Wisconsin teachers, and
the student-to-teacher pipeline.
The takeaway...
- I want you to...
- Sara: [exhaling]
We have a lot more work to do.
- Seymour: Shaw says, ideally...
- That the diversity of the
student body would be reflected
in the diversity of
the teacher population.
- Seymour: While almost one
third of students in Wisconsin
are students of color, only
about 6% of their teachers are,
and many don't stay.
- Teachers of color who come
into the workforce are leaving
at a faster rate
than our white teachers.
- Okay?
- Seymour: Many educators
say a diverse teaching staff
positively impacts all students
in a lot of different ways.
- We see positive impacts
across everything
from student motivation
to strong student-teacher
relationships,
to absenteeism, graduation rates
and going on to college.
- When you look
at the educational inequities,
I think it is
just intrinsically tied
to the inequities
that are in society,
but it's gonna take
policy changes--
not just talk.
- For his part,
Verona Superintendent Clardy
is moving beyond talking
and taking action.
- I'm not a worrier;
I'm a doer.
And so we're about
doing the work.
- We continue our reporting
on race and education
in the state of Wisconsin
here from the campus
of the University of Wisconsin
in Madison.
Here to continue
the conversation,
we're joined by Dr. Alex Gee
from the Nehemiah Center
for Urban Leadership
and Development.
Mr. Kaleem Caire, Superintendent
of One City Schools
here in Madison,
and Dr. Courtney Bell,
who is the director
of the Wisconsin Center
for Educational Research.
As I've traveled and talked
to folks across the state
about this issue,
I get the sense
that it's a very touchy subject.
Is there something to that?
- Race is a touchy subject
in the United States.
I think, when we think
about systemic racism,
which exists in education,
we think about these sort
of interlocking layers
of systems and policies, right?
So, you only need
to think about
how do we draw
the district boundary,
and the way that interacts
with the neighborhoods,
the neighborhood
attendance zone,
the teachers
the school can attract,
the outcomes that then wind up
in that neighborhood,
that those
are interlocking systems.
So, it is contentious, I think
partly because people do care,
but the persistent inequalities
are hard to look at
in this state,
in particular.
- Dr. Gee, why are people
afraid to talk about this?
- Because I think
it's difficult
to face up to the culpability.
We like to quote statistics,
but we don't really want
to look at our ownership
in the problem
or why we've allowed
it to persist.
In educational services systems,
we want to fight
against racism,
but when we don't
properly address it,
the educational systems
themselves
become breeding grounds
for racism.
And I think we just like
to pass the buck
to someone else without
taking full responsibility.
- I think they're both
absolutely spot on,
but I also think that
we have divorced ourselves
from the problem.
That it is not only something
that I'm embarrassed
or don't want to be culpable in,
but it's been persistent
for so long,
and if I know about it,
I'm tired of hearing of it,
and so, it brings me down.
I've heard people say that,
like,
"I can't focus on the problem
'cause it just brings me down.
"'Cause it's like
we've not solved it,
it's not gonna be solved."
And so, I think
there's a lot of hopelessness.
I also think that we also
live in a state that,
by and large, has been
privileged for a very long time,
particularly in the area
where we are in Madison.
And so, when you're privileged,
and things are going okay,
and you don't have to
focus on the issue,
you act like it doesn't exist.
- But this lack of success
that we're seeing,
is it more to blame
on the teachers,
or is it more to blame
on students?
- I think there's enough blame
to go around, actually.
But I think, if we ignore
the systemic issues,
and only point fingers to the
parents, the students, teachers,
not look
at the larger issue,
I think we continue just
to kick the can down the road.
And so, I think we have to
look at really how we got here.
I think what makes it
even more difficult is
that education has been deemed
the great equalizer.
Education is what brings you
into the mainstream,
and it keeps you from being
discriminated against.
It keeps you from being poor.
And when that system
that's meant to elevate us
is keeping certain people down
it's the antithesis
to what we think
of when we think
about education.
And then,
we have to really begin
to ask ourselves
real tough questions.
But we're trying
to educate children
in a system, in a world,
in a reality
where there's
so much brokenness and pain,
and disregard
for who they are,
their pain, and their culture.
So, I think we really need
an overhaul
in how we even look at
what education means for us.
- And we know a lot of times
we find solutions looking
at other communities,
other school districts,
things like that.
Dr. Bell, we know you work
across the world, the country,
looking at different ways
people do research
to solve these kinds of issues.
Is there any district
out there anywhere
that's doing things well in
terms of addressing these issues
with Black and brown
students falling behind?
- You know there
are success cases.
My colleague
Gudiel R. Crosthwaite
is the superintendent
in Lynwood Unified,
which is in LA.
They have
community-based schools.
They have colleagues of color,
professionals of color
in those school buildings.
Not only colleagues of color,
but some.
They are committed.
They believe
that all those kids can learn.
They have tons of AP courses
in those high schools.
They are starting
with early Pre-K.
And so, they hold them tight,
and they treat them
with dignity,
and those families with
dignity the whole way up.
- Now Kaleem, you've built
a pretty unique environment
in One City.
What are some of the things
that you're doing
that you feel like
other districts can learn from?
- Well, there's
quite a few things.
First and foremost, it's
the number of our young people
that are coming to us who
are so far behind academically.
Doesn't matter
the grade level that they're at,
but it's even more depressing
when they come to you in 9th
and 10th grade and who have a...
We have a third of our kids
are at the--
somewhere between 1st and 4th
grade level in math and reading.
It's like you just pass them
along to 9th and 10th grade
without intervening to address
their real core challenges.
First six to eight weeks,
we get to know our kids.
Then we pivot
'cause we see where they're at.
We test 'em, we look
at what they're,
how they interact in school,
how they show up
as students every day.
And two hours in the morning
students are in math.
Two hours in the afternoon,
they're in language arts,
and it's not just
instruction all day.
The first part of that
is instruction at their level.
And then we bring in tutors
that we've trained.
We've trained
over 50 tutors to come in,
and work with them one-on-one,
no more than one-on-two
to help them
to get up to grade levels.
So we have a personalized
learning environment for them
so we can move them forward.
So we won't be passing
kids in our school forward
to 9th and 10th grade
who aren't ready to be there.
- Dr. Gee, you've got one
superpower I'm gonna give you
to fix this problem.
What are you gonna do with it?
- We've got to really embed
the importance
of helping students to...
and I'll speak specifically
to our work
with African American children
with really understanding
and appreciating the culture.
You know, if we were to
go back in time 60 years ago,
we would not be having
this conversation.
Black people were going to
historically Black
colleges and universities.
Building historically Black
colleges and universities,
building churches
and businesses,
highly successful educationally
with integration.
And one of my mentors,
and she probably
has mentored all of us,
Dr. Gloria
Ladson-Billings has always said,
"But, Alex, remember,
with integration,
30,000 Black teachers
lost their jobs
'cause they did not,
they were not integrated."
- Seymour: That's right.
- Black students were,
Black teachers weren't,
and many of them
became domestics.
And so, we have to understand
that this is somewhat new.
Because again, 60 years ago,
we weren't saying,
"How do we educate
our Black children?"
We were probably asking,
"How do we vote?"
But Black children
were becoming
dentists and doctors
and nurses and professors,
and then something happened.
So my superpower would be,
let's get them in places
where teachers can relate
to them, understand them,
celebrate them, and where they
see themselves in textbooks.
I came to Madison advanced
in 2nd grade,
but I had a Black teacher
in 1st grade who told me
I was gonna be the president
of the United States.
She's 102 years old,
and we're still pen pals.
We're talking is if
we have to fix Black children.
What we have to
really ask ourselves is,
"How are we
breaking Black children?"
- So, we know most parts
of Wisconsin
have a very tiny population
of students of color,
if any at all.
So when you talk about the folks
that sit at home right now,
and say, "This has
nothing to do with me."
How do we get those
folks to have a stake
in this game to
make things better?
- I'd like to go back to
something that was said earlier
about the function
of education in,
and I'll say, a democracy.
This affects all of us,
every single one of us,
no matter what
our racial background is,
no matter where we live.
If we do not have democracy,
that functions with civility,
where people can consider
issues of science
in the public domain of policy
around all manner of things:
housing, power, you name it,
all the things,
social services, farm subsidies,
whatever it may be.
We need an educated citizenry.
That's what the country
was founded on.
So for me,
this is about all of us.
These are all of our children;
this is our country.
- And I would say
America's at risk.
If you produce children
who lack an interest,
and passion to solve the big
problems of today and tomorrow,
who's gonna be there
to solve them?
We have to focus on education
and make it, I believe,
our number one priority
in this country.
And if we want a country
that's not divided,
we also have to have
a education that unifies people
rather than divides them.
And so if we do those things,
we'll succeed.
If not, you know, our demise
is we already have signs
of what
it will look like.
- If we don't learn
how to work together,
and work for and with,
be educated by,
and educating people
who don't look like us,
we can't fool
ourselves in thinking
that we're ready
for a global market,
that we want to compete
in the global market.
And so,
we can't boast of having
world-class
school districts or universities
if we don't know
how to talk to people
who are from our own state
who look different.
And so, I think we have to own
the broader problem.
Otherwise, we can't boast
in producing people
who can compete internationally
for jobs,
or awards, or opportunities.
- Seymour: We'll have
to leave it there, Dr. Gee.
Thank you, sir.
- My pleasure.
- Kaleem Caire, thank you.
- Thank you.
- Dr. Courtney Bell,
we appreciate you.
And we thank you folks at home
for joining us as well.
[gentle, poignant music]
- Announcer: Funding for
Wisconsin in Black & White
is provided by
Ira and Ineva Reilly Baldwin
Wisconsin Idea Endowment,
DeAtley Family Foundation.
Joe and Mary Ellyn
Sensenbrenner.
Lau and Bea Christensen.
The Evjue Foundation,
the charitable arm
of The Capital Times,
Madison College,
National Guardian
Life Insurance Company,
UnityPoint Health -
Meriter,
donors to
the Focus Fund for Journalism,
and Friends
of PBS Wisconsin.